I am an assistant
professor at Washington State University
in the Department
of Digital Technology and Culture.
And this is my project.
A quick overview of this project.
I'll talk a bit about the background
research on video game dialog texts.
I'll mention a few details about this
fledgling corpus and where I intend
to go from here, so you can access a link
to the files that I put up on the site.
But emphasize
this is very much a work in progress.
My background is in linguistics
with a focus on French,
and I've done some work on corpus
linguistics before,
and I'm also a fan of video
games and RPGs.
So this is bringing a few things together.
We're looking at ludolinguistics here,
and previous research has focused on
recognizing video game dialog
as legitimate sources
for discourse analysis, just like in film,
books, other media.
If we look at how language is created
and used in video games
such as in RPGs,
previous studies have looked at how—
male versus female characters,
there's a domination—
dominated by male character speech,
about 70% in some studies,
and also that male characters
tend to be associated
with more objective speech,
whereas female characters are more
receiving action that is done upon them.
We can also use a corpus
linguistics of video
game dialog to look at
how developers can create dialog
that is gender neutral, or to use
non-binary language, not only because
we have different genders of gamers,
but also as a way
of creating dialog
when we don't have the full context
from the developers.
So for character, is writing to it
or speaking to another character,
we don't know the gender.
This could
pose a challenge for languages,
depending on the grammar of the language,
and we're looking at pre-scripted
video game dialog.
So we're not talking about voice chat
or gamer chats in like multiplayer games.
Probably the best example of this corpus
approach is the Video Game Dialog Corpus
that Rennick and Roberts and their team
at Cardiff University have developed.
So they've taken several dozen RPGs
and compiled the dialog into texts,
into a corpus of over 6 million words
that's really available online.
It's mostly in English.
They have done some work with non-English
texts, such as in Mass Effect.
They looked at how the English “you”
is rendered in French and Spanish,
because you have to distinguish
between two forms of “you.”
And they saw that localizations
in this case
tend to be more overly formal.
So this is a challenge for localizations.
There are
different ways that we can access
the game text to create these corpora.
Sometimes it's as simple
as accessing fan transcriptions
or community transcriptions online.
It's just that these are heavily
dominated by English.
There's very few non-English
game strips out there on the Internet.
If you have access to the game files,
you can extract the text directly.
It's just that this is not always easy
or technically feasible,
depending on the game.
And it is also, of course, possible
to just play through the game
and write down the dialog, or increasingly
go on the YouTube and watch or play
through or “Let's Play.” The problem,
though, is that these walkthroughs tend
to not include
all of the possible dialog options,
because in most RPGs
you have branching dialog options.
And so we don't have a full
we don't have the complete dialog
for a lot of these games, especially
non-English games.
And also access to
these videos can be removed at any time.
So we don't necessarily
have a stable repository of these texts.
So again, if you are looking for texts
in English, it's pretty easy to find them
with a simple search.
So there's several examples.
If you take a game like 67, there's
the original or the remake versions.
But if you look for other languages,
the text of this game and other languages
in German, there is exactly one hit
for a published script in German,
but it's just one playthrough.
It's not a complete dialog.
Similar thing in Spanish.
There's one publication online
that has the script as a playthrough,
so we don't, again,
don't have the complete dialog.
And then in French, there's pretty much
nothing at all in text formats
available online
for the dialog of Final Fantasy VII.
So I did it.
What I would consider it extensive search
of a lot of snippets of dialog, and I
found nothing.
So I thought that this corpus
could give us a repository for these texts
that especially those that
are in other languages besides English,
and collect them in a single location.
We can then, with multiple languages,
make cross-linguistic comparisons.
So we would do parallel concordances,
where you can use an application
like Sketch Engine to compare search
for how a specific word
or phrase is translated
from one language to another.
We can also add metadata so that we can
search for particular characteristics,
such as the character who's
speaking or their age, gender, and so on.
Okay, so I'll just give you a few details
with this fledgling corpus,
and it's going to be based on Final
Fantasy VII, as you probably
guess.
And so right now I'm in the process
since I'm working with French.
And I had to start from scratch.
Basically, I have about 26,000 words
that I've transcribed
from the English text that are provided,
that have been provided online.
I won't go into too much detail about
the process, but I did use the game text.
I was able to extract the text from them.
So this slide gives you those details.
But I was working with a JSON text
that the Video Game Dialog Corpus
has made available,
so I cross-reference with that.
The JSON files
give you basically a readable
text version of the files,
and the Video Game
Dialog Corpus can be found on GitHub.
I give you an example
of the French version
that I've assembled with the link there.
And that's on the Google site.
The Video Game Dialog Corpus
also has a visual representation
of branching dialog options.
It's not just for Baldur's Gate.
You can upload any JSON file
that's properly formatted
and you get a visual representation here.
So I hope to be able to incorporate
this in the future.
So Sketch
Engine is an online tool that allows
for parallel concordance extraction.
What that means again
is, if we have an aligned corpus.
So every line of dialog
in one language is aligned on the same row
in an Excel file with every line of dialog
in another language.
And we can use.
Or I used our scripts to convert the JSON
files into the appropriate Excel format.
So you can see an example of
that, of an Excel file
that I uploaded to the Google site.
You do have to sign— create an account
for Sketch Engine,
so that would take too much time
to demonstrate here.
So I just have some snippets
that I can show you.
The word plates in English is important
in the context of this game,
but it was translated
poorly in some examples of dialog.
It should be “plaque,” the second example,
versus “plateau.” So we can find
discrepancies much more easily
than searching through individual texts
using this parallel concordance option.
Or we can go the other way.
You can start with the other language,
like in French.
If you want to look for the word “ami,”
or “friend,” we can see that
there is some confusion
or possible ambiguity with the translators
and distinguishing between
“friend” and “girlfriend” for example.
And it's not just for comparing
two languages.
We can compare multiple languages.
I'm working on the Spanish
and German texts right now
so that we can look at, for example,
an enigmatic expression
like “to settle the score.”
How is this rendered across
different localizations
and even fan translations,
which is often the source of texts.
And then an
example with metadata we can tag
for a specific character, for example.
So I give an example, screenshots
here from the Sketch Engine outputs.
Which character references
the other character more often.
So we see that.
For example, Tifa mentions Cloud’s
name more often than Cloud mentions
Tifa’s name in their dialog.
So if the code for use metadata
to code for
the names of characters,
and the example of that Excel file
is also available on my site.
Okay, so quick recap here.
The main goal here
is to create a central repository
for video game dialog,
especially of non-English text,
because those are the most scarce online.
And I would like this caucus to be useful
for disciplines
connected to ludolinguistics.
So as you can see, translation
or localization studies, discourse
analysis, gender analysis,
and especially keeping with ELO’s mission,
the preservation of these texts
and the free dissemination of these texts.
Okay, think I'm out of time.
I do have some slides on where
I would like to take this corpus, but
I could answer some of those questions
in the Q&A, so I'll stop there.
Thank you.